William Lescaze Papers
William Lescaze Papers
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs
    - Printed material, exhibition and exposition catalogues and announcements (Box 62)
  - Printed material
    - by Lescaze, 3 folders (Box 62)
    - On being an architect by WL (Box 62)
    - The intent of the artist by Sherwood Anderson, 2 copies (Box 62)
    - The intent of the artist by Thornton Wilder (Box 62)
    - The intent of the artist by Roger Sessions (Box 62)
    - The intent of the artist by William Lescaze (Box 62)
    - About Lescaze, On being an architect (Box 62)
    - About Lescaze, 5 folders (Box 62)
    - The story of our time (Encyclopedia yearbook) (Box 62)
    - Art and the machine by Sheldon and Martha Cheney (Box 62)
    - Tomorrow's house by Nelson Wright (Box 62)
    - "The new world architecture" by Sheldon Cheney (Box 63)
    - The role of William Lescaze in the introduction of the international style to the United States, by Lanmon, 1979; dissertation, University of Delaware (Box 63)
    - New York's Turtle Bay: old and new by Delaney (Box 63)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Clippings, includes Unity House, other jobs (Oversize 14)
    - Clippings (Oversize 15)
    - Clippings (Oversize 16)
- Architectural works
  For many of these projects there is also material -- drawings, blueprints, and other material -- in the first series in the collection ("Individual commissions"). This material is arranged by project number. Refer to the Alphabetical index of projects at the end of this finding aid to locate this material.
  - Ansonia High School (Box 63)
  - Aviation Building (Box 63)
  - Bernhard Residence (Box 63)
  - Butler House (Box 63)
  - Buttenwieser (Box 63)
  - Calderone Theater (Box 63)
  - Candlewood Lake (Box 63)
  - CBS, 2 folders (Box 63)
  - Cates House (Box 63)
  - Cinerama (Box 63)
  - City and Municipal Courts Building (Box 63)
  - Crawford House (Box 63)
  - Crossett House (Box 63)
  - Curry House (Box 63)
  - Dartington Hall (Box 63)
  - Dune Hotel (Box 63)
  - Dunn (Box 63)
  - Fenestra (Box 63)
  - Field House (Box 63)
  - Goucher College (Box 63)
  - Harbor House (Box 63)
  - Henderson Theater (Box 63)
  - Hessian Hills (Box 63)
  - Hobart House (Box 63)
  - Kramer House (Box 63)
  - Lescazes Homes (Box 63)
  - Levey House (Box 63)
  - Loomis House (Box 63)
  - Mali Playroom (Box 63)
  - Manhattanville Houses (Box 63)
  - Museum of Modern Art (Box 63)
  - Norman House (Box 63)
  - Norwood School (Box 63)
  - Oak Lane Country Day (Box 63)
  - Philadelphia Savings Fund Society, 6 folders (Box 63)
  - Prefabricated Houses (Box 63)
  - Spinny Hills (Box 63)
  - Stowkowski Apartment (Box 63)
  - Swiss Embassy (Box 63)
  - Swiss Pavilion (Box 63)
  - J. W. Thompson Company (Box 63)
  - Unity House (Box 63)
  - Wilbour Library (Box 63)
  - Williams C. D. (Box 63)
  - Williamsburg Houses (Box 63)
  - Woods End Apartment (Box 63)
  - No. 2 Broadway (Box 63)
  - No. 30 West Broadway (Box 63)
  - No. 300 East 42nd Street (Box 63)
  - No. 711 Third Avenue (Box 63)
  - No. 777 Third Avenue (Box 63)
- Writings
  - On architecture, 1937; undate; 2 items (Box 64)
  - On architecture, 1937-1954 (Box 64)
  - On being an architect
    - Research material and photographs (Box 64)
    - Manuscript, typescript (Box 64)
    - Manuscript, typescript, 1941-1942 (Box 64)
    - Early version? partial (Box 64)
    - Book reviews, 1943; 1949 (Box 64)
    - Book reviews by WL with correspondence (Box 64)
  - Lectures
    - 1928-1932 (Box 65)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 65)
    - 1934-1938 (Lescaze?) (Box 65)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 65)
    - 1939-1964 (Lescaze?) (Box 65)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 65)
    - 1940-1943 (Box 65)
    - 1945 (Box 65)
    - 1951-1963 (Box 65)
    - Correspondence (Box 65)
    - Slides (Box 65)
    - Miscellaneous material (Box 65)
  - Lescaze(?) notebook with sketches, circa 1918 (Box 65)
  - Lescaze and N.B. Brainerd / Wealth or the thrift of the city plan, 1921; play; Photoplay scenario TMS (Box 65)
  - Radio interviews, 1938-1954 (Box 65)
  - Notes, lecture, 1932-1969; includes clippings and excerpts from others (Box 65)
  - Unidentified (Box 65)
  - Notes, miscellaneous, 1920?-1968; undated (Box 65)
  - Smith, L.W. / Art or Insanity - which?, 1933 (Box 66)
  - Wingert, Paul S. / William Lescaze: Modern American Architect (Box 66)
  - About Lescaze (Box 66)
  - By others, quotes and notes (Box 66)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 66)
Alphabetical index of projects
The index below lists all projects alphabetically, followed by their corresponding project number(s). Those with no number may be found in the inventory above, in the section entitled "Individual commissions: Unnumbered projects."
1 New York Plaza 1306
1 New York Plaza, alterations 1452
1 Oliver Plaza, Pittsburgh 1330
1 Oliver Plaza, Pittsburgh, revisions, 1376
10 East 70th Street, NYC 1140
110 East 59th Street, NYC1242 1360
111 Pine Street, San Francisco 1064
1155 Raymond Avenue Building, Newark, NJ 1477
1200 Market St. [PSFS?] [no number]
2 Broadway Building, NYC 1050
2 New York Plaza, Broad & South Sts, NYC 1411
200 East 58th apartments, NYC 1101
200 South Michigan Avenue, Chicago 1241
245 Park Avenue, NYC 1125
250 Greenwich Avenue, NYC 1116
30 West Broadway, NYC 1072
300 East 42nd Building, NYC 1185
345 Park Avenue/580 Lexington Avenue, NYC 1265
59th St. & Madison Avenue office building, NYC 1204
711 Third Avenue, NYC 951
74 West 92nd apartments, NYC 1161
777 Third Avenue Building, NYC 1194
905 Third Avenue, Post Office Building, NYC 1249
979 Third Avenue Rothschild showroom and offices, NYC 1229
Amos Parrish & Co. offices, NYC 228
An American House [no number]
Andrew Geller Shoe Stores showroom, NYC 251
Ansonia High School, Ansonia, CT 419
Apartment house and garage project, NYC 252
Apartment house lobby alterations, Washington, DC 639
Apartment house project, Park Avenue and 72nd Street [no number]
Architectural Forum design for filling station, NYC 695
Arden Gallery penthouse duplex, NYC 256
Astoria-Queens housing development, NYC 340
Aviation Building, World's Fair, NYC 582
Barber and beauty shop, Grand Central Station [no number]
Barnes, Mrs. Joseph, alterations, NYC 643A
Belmont Hill School additions, Belmont, MA 813
Borg-Warner Building, Chicago, IL 1025
Briggs Haberdashery, NYC 272
Brooklyn Children's Museum, NYC 386
Brooklyn Museum auditorium, NYC 391
Brotherhood-In-Action House, 40th St. & 7th Avenue, NYC 1108
Brunswick-Balke-Collender billiard tables 406
Butler, William weekend residence, Harvey Cedars, NJ 432
Buttenweiser, Benjamin J. apartment, 450 East 52nd St., NYC 1086
Buttenweiser, Benjamin J. alteration, Bedford, NY 614B
Buttenweiser, Benjamin J. child's bedroom, NYC 673
Buttenweiser, Lawrence apartment, 5th Avenue & 89th St, NYC 1135
Buttenweiser, Mrs. Benjamin J. town house, 17 East 73rd, NYC 396
Calderone Theatre, Hempstead, NY 767
Cates, Vincent K. residence, Melrose, MA 407
CBS display room, NYC 417
CBS elevator study, NYC 444
CBS little theater, NYC 410
CBS microphones, NYC431 751
CBS miscellaneous accessories, NYC 418
CBS mobile unit, NYC 779
CBS Studios, Hollywood 515
CBS Studios, NYC405 426 443 549-570
CBS Studios, San Francisco, CA531 549-570
CBS Theater #4, West 53rd St, NYC 706
CBS Theater, West 45th Street, NYC 398
CBS, 18th floor lobby, NYC 1017
CBS-WBBM Studios, Chicago, IL 501
CBS-WCAU auditorium alteration, Philadelphia, PA 600
CBS, unidentified jobs [no number]
Chase Manhattan Bank canopies, NYC 1388
Chatham Plaza Center, Pittsburgh, PA 1284
Chelsea houses, NYC 643
Cherry Lawn School alteration, Darien CT 617A
Cherry Lawn School boy's dormitory 617B
Cherry Lawn School, Darien, CT 723
Chicopee Sales Corporation offices, NYC 761
Children's Haven hospital, NYC 364
Christie-Forsythe housing development, NYC 322
Churchill apartment house, Los Angeles, CA 1121
Churston Development hotel, 4th batch houses 455
Churston Development hotel, 2d batch houses 451
Churston Development hotel, 3rd batch houses 454
Churston Development hotel, 1st, Devon, England 247
Churston Estate housing development, Devon, England 346
Cinerama Theater alterations, NYC 941
City and Municipal Courts Building, NYC786 1000
City Athletic Club addition, NYC 763
City for children planning study, East Harlem 740
Cocktail shaker design 402
Community House for La Chaux de Fonds 1919 [no number]
Country House for Young Couple, commissioned for Architecture Forum 1927 [no number]
Crawford, Mrs. George guest house, Greenwich, CT 630
Creedmoor Hospital rehabilitation center, Queens, NY 1325
Crosset Health Center, Crosset, AR 760
Crowley, Jerome residence alterations, South Bend, IN 1083
Crowley, Jerome residence, South Bend, IN 791
Crown Central Petroleum Corporation filling station, Baltimore 789
Dartington Hall boarding School, South Devon, England 347
Dartington Hall cottages 369
Dartington Hall gymnasium 356
Dartington Hall residence for Kurt Jooss, South Devon, England 393
Dartington Hall nursery school 355
Dartington Hall offices and laboratory 357
Dartington Hall offices 323
Dartington Hall piggery 358
Dartington Hall theater 375
Dartington Hall, headmaster's residence (W.B. Curry) 304
Dartington Hall, junior school only 304B
de Sieyes, Jean hunting lodge, Mt. Kisco, NY 220
Diploma Project, Large building block in Zurich 1919 [no number]
Dorie-Miller East Harlem Housing Project, NYC 686
Dorothy Gray store front, NYC 339
Downstate Medical Center Garage, Brooklyn 1282
Dreyfus, Herbert M. apartment, NYC 275
Dune Deck Hotel 873
Dune Deck Hotel, Westhampton Beach, NY 1045
Dunn, Frederick S. cottage, Woodbridge, CT 604
Dunn, Frederick S. residence, Woodbridge, CT 509
Durisol, Inc., residence, Aberdeen, MD 862
Edgewood School 1924 [no number]
Editorial Publications office alterations, NYC 381
Elementary School Norwood, NJ 785
Elliot Houses alterations 749
Emerson Radio Cabinet design, NYC 713
Fain, W.H. [Williams] residence 520
Ferguson, Alice apartment house, NYC 214
Field, Frederick V. apartment, NYC 507
Field, Frederick V. guest house, New Hartford, CT 658
Field, Frederick V. residence addition, Hartford, CT 514
Field, Frederick V. residence alterations, NYC 832
Field, Frederick V. residence, New Hartford, CT 301
First National City Bank World's Fair exhibition building, NYC 1195
Ford, Simeon residence, 2 Sutton Square, NYC 131
Fox motion picture theater 318
Frank Vance Storrs offices 313
Frederick Loeser Exhibition Rooms, Brooklyn 226
Froelich, Howard residence, NYC 409
Future American Country House, Commissioned for Architectural Record 1928 [no number]
Garage at Queensborough Bridge, NYC 586
Garage roof, Albany, NY 1422
Goldwater Memorial Hospital auditorium and chapels, NYC 1225
Good, Lloyd weekend residence, Harvey Cedars, N.J 432
Goucher College competition, Baltimore 598
Government of India tourist information office, 11 East 58th NYC 962
Grand Central Building [no number]
Gustavson, John residence, Harvey Cedars, N.J 512
Halle Brothers Exhibition 1928 [no number]
Hanna Building [no number]
Harbor Homes housing development. Port Washington (Long Island), NY 849A
Harding, Mrs. Charles salon, NYC 270
Hartmann, Dr. G.W. residence, State College, PA 361
Hattie Carnegie shop 316
Herzberg, Ben apartment, NYC 276
Hessian Hills School, Croton-on-Hudson, NY 312
Hobart residence, alterations, Paterson, N.J 634
Hobart residence, Tuxedo Park, NY 588
HOPE Windows, Inc., Jamestown NY 717
Hotel converted to apartments, Detroit, MI 1271
House of 2039 Project [no number]
House of the Future [no number]
Howe and Lescaze office, Philadelphia 289
India Exchange, Ltd. Calcutta 937
J. Walter Thompson, office for Ruth Waldo, NYC408 896
J. Walter Thompson, office layout, NYC 704
J. Walter Thompson offices, NYC 516
Johnson & Johnson research building, New Brunswick, NJ 738
Junior High School #24, Richmond (Staten Island), NY 1300
Kaye, Sydney, residence, Cornwall Bridge, CT 874
Kimble Glass, office building. Vineland, N.J 523
Kimble Glass, superintendent's offices, Vineland, N.J 548
Kootz, Samuel residence [no number]
Kramer, Raymond C. town house, 32 East 74th, NYC 379
Laurel Hill housing development, NYC 345
League of Nations [no number]
Lescaze residence, 211 East 48th, NYC 602
Levey, Sherwin S. residence, Candlewood Lake, CT 810
Libby-Owen-Ford Building, World's Fair, NYC 584
London Shoe showroom, NYC 247
Longfellow Building, Washington, DC 619
Loomis, Alfred residence, Easthampton, NY 780
Loomis, Alfred residence, Tuxedo Park, NY 517
Macy exhibition, penthouse studio, NYC 232
Magnolia Petroleum exposition building, Dallas, TX 440
Maison, Bertie beauty parlor, NYC 255
Mali, Mrs. playroom, NYC 545
Manhasset housing project, Manhasset, NY 1100
Manhattanville Houses, NYC 1009
Markel, Howard country house, Redding, CT 542
May, Stacy cottage, Martha's Vineyard, MA 606
Mayfair Theatre, 47th St. & 7th Avenue, NYC 1107
Meloney, William Brown alteration at Sutton Square, NYC 1923 771
Meridian Housing Corporation 1936 [no number]
Methodist Church Center, East 44th St, NYC 1183
Metro North housing project, East Harlem 1318
Metropolitan Museum of Art, American Industrial Art Exhibition, NYC 387
Metropolitan Museum of Art, exhibition, NYC 623
Meyer, S.T. apartment store, NYC 239
Monsanto Chemical Company, NYC 692
Monterey Tower limited dividend housing, 180th St. & Monterey Avenue, Bronx 1136
Moulin Rouge Restaurant alterations, NYC 185
Museum of Modern Art project, NYC 295
Nash, Frederick V. country house, Minneapolis, MN 532
Norman, Edward A. residence, 124 East 70th, NYC 628
Nudelman & Conti showroom, NYC 236
NY Housing Trust prefab research, NYC 800
NYSE site study, NYC 1363
Oak Lane Country Day School, Philadelphia 258
Painted drapery for a restaurant 1924 [no number]
Parking terminal, Boston, MA 725
Pass & Seymour lighting fixture designs, Syracuse, NY 688
Peck, Arthur residence, Paoli, PA 286
Pennsylvania Museum of Art children's room, Philadelphia, PA 320
Philadelphia Saving Fund Society, building, Philadelphia, PA 284
Philadelphia Saving Fund Society, garage, Philadelphia, PA 297
Philadelphia Saving Fund Society, vault, Philadelphia, PA 121
Phillips, R. Colfax apartment, NYC 222
Pittsburg Plate Glass commercial, Pittsburgh, PA 719
Plainview Jewish Community Center, Long Island NY 1015
Porcelain Enamel Institute research 930
Porter, Mrs. George French residence, Ojai, CA 277
Post Office, Hicksville (Long Island), NY 1305
Psi Upsilon Fraternity Club House, Dartmouth College, Hanover, NH 335
Public School 14, Richmond (Staten Island) NY 787
Purdue University small house, Purdue, IN 434
Queensbridge housing development, NYC 377
Radio station, Reykjavik, Iceland 777
Reliance Steel Corporation prefab houses, Pittsburgh, PA 801
Republic Steel penthouse, Cleveland, OH 917
River Gardens housing development, NYC 336
Rogers, Bernard residence, Rochester, NY 519
Salamanca Housing Project, Salamanca, NY 985
Scarsdale Recreation Survey, Scarsdale, NY 759
School of Industrial Art, NYC 980
Sculptors Guild exhibition, NYC 1952 928
Shore Club Towers, Detroit, MI 1120
Silvray lamps 411
Sinkler, James M. R. residence, Philadelphia, PA 117
Soldiers and Sailors Monument 1928 [no number]
Speed-Park garage study 1222
Speiser, Maurice J. residence, Philadelphia, PA [no number]
Spelman Prentice farmhouse alterations, Wheelock, VT 700
Spinney Hill Homes, Manhasset, NY 849B
Spivacke, Harold residence, Washington, D.C 622
Spreter, Roy F. residence and garage, Ardmore, PA 360
State Building Code Commission 900
Stern's Department Store alteration, NYC 1224
Stokowski, Leopold apartment, NYC 241
Stone, Maurice bedroom, NYC 648
Stratford Tower apartments, NYC 1263
Sutton House apartments, NYC 942
Swiss Embassy Chancellery Building, Washington, D.C 1057
Swiss Embassy interiors, Washington, D.C 1092
Swiss Pavilion, World's Fair, NYC 597
Sydenham Hospital addition, NYC 844
Tapestry design for theatre, New Haven, CT 180
The Kawneer Company consulting, Miles, MI 694
Theatre and store building for Carl Brunson Hollywood, CA 1926 157
Time, Inc. offices, NYC 518
Trans Lux motion picture theaters, NYC 307
U.S. Mission to the U.N. office layouts, NYC 1014
Unity House camp, Bushkill, PA 397
Unity Lap Robe Co. showroom, NYC 259
UNIWALL research, second stage 831
Wallace, William Kay country house, Bedford Village, NY 380
Warehouse for the Board of Education, Cleveland, OH 1922 [no number]
Washington Market commercial, warehouse and industrial buildings, NYC 1285
Washington Street Market project, NYC 1160
Wasserman, William Stix office, Philadelphia 314
Wasserman, William Stix residence, Whitemarsh, PA107B 262
Webb & Knapp addition, NYC 931
Webb & Knapp alterations, NYC 899
Wertheim, Maurice residence, Cos Cob, CT 321
Wilbour Library alterations, Brooklyn 366
Williamsburg housing project, NYC 388
Willow Garden Restaurant 133
WLW Studios, Cincinnati, OH 684
Woods End defense housing, Roselle, N.J 680
WOR building sign, NYC 731